Welcome back to On The Brink, this is Nick Carter.
I'm with Anthony Yim, the co-founder of Artemis.
Thanks for coming.
Thanks for having me.
So this is a very auspicious day, this is our second report we've done together.
That's pretty cool, man, what a great working relationship we have.
Thank you, yeah.
When I thought about the report, the first person I came to was you guys.
I really enjoyed working with you guys last time and wanted to outdo our last report and
come up with something even cooler.
Yeah, I think this one blows last year's one out of the water.
I think it was very interesting to do an actual survey of stablecoin users, but this is the
holy grail.
This is what people always ask me about, is it the same for you?
Yeah, I do think that two reports are also pretty complimentary, one's like qualitative
and quantitative.
So I don't want to, I also don't want to like poo poo our work from last year.
It's just, I think they go hand in hand and we just have a much clearer picture of what's
going on and because there's just so much BS like metrics and stories and sensationalist
articles out there that come up and I was just tired of it.
Yeah, and you know, skeptics will ask me all the time, hey, well, like, okay, we see that
there's 10 trillion or whatever dollars of stablecoin volume a year, but like, how much
of that's real?
Like how much is real payments?
So I guess that's the premise of this report.
So tell us about how we actually went about getting the answer, not the answer, but an
answer.
Yeah.
Well, you know, I think I took a page from from the Nick Carter book of you can just
do things.
And so and so, you know, for the last really year, you know, as a data company, we've been
getting asked questions by everyone in crypto and fintech of like, hey, how much steam coin
payments volume is there really, how, you know, who's using it?
Where are they?
And so at some point, I just got tired of having no answer for for people.
And I was like, wait, I can just go do things.
And I just called up as many steam coin players in the space and be like, look, you know,
we're trying to we're trying to like, lift up the space together.
I think crypto has this bad rep where it's just used for speculation.
We have all this like anecdotal evidence that it's not it's it's also used by real people
for real use cases, but we don't have the data to back it.
And so I yeah, I think with you, you know, I think I remember calling you up a couple
of months ago and be like, hey, I want to try and do this report together.
And and you were super enthusiastic.
And so I think after that, I just started calling up all the major players like BBNK
and conduit and getting them on this, getting them to share the data with us.
Yeah. And I want to also shout out Dragonfly and Rob Hadek here because Dragonfly are
our co-authors and partners on the report.
But I mean, I think it's absolutely remarkable.
We were able to get 20 different stable coin payment firms, whatever you want to call them,
plus an additional 11 firms with estimates from from your team's wizardry based on on-chain
data mainly for a total of 31 firms to participate.
I mean, we know there's more, but we still bid off a huge share of the market.
What's your guess of sort of like roughly how how much completeness we have in this estimate?
My figure would answer is probably like 75 percent, 80 percent.
What do you think?
I mean, between Binance, BBNK, Conduit, Reap, those are probably the biggest ones.
Bitso, Felix, Yellow Card.
I mean, that is if you read the report, I think our exit estimate for stable coin payment
run rate is 73 billion dollars as of February of this year, which is definitely more now,
by the way, but that was just our cut off for the data.
I guess the question is, like, how do you how do you think about that number?
So let's say maybe close to 100 by now, 100 billion a year of stable coin payments,
like real payments where we know who's sending, who's receiving.
We know what kind of activity it is.
How do you compare that against the trillions of stable coin settlement we see on-chain?
Well, first off, I think we're very, very early and it's really exciting to be in
stable coins because I did some rough math.
I think for the B2B volume alone, it's been growing something like 400 percent year over year.
And I was reading actually visas like earnings report from last quarter,
and they had this slide on the TAM for B2B payments.
I think they clocked it at 145 trillion.
And so we're still less than one percent there with stable coins.
And so I think we're exactly around like 0.03 percent or something.
So three bit.
Yeah. So our estimate for B2B is three billion monthly as of February,
which is up from basically zero in 2023.
Yeah, exactly. So 145 trillion, 100 billion.
Yeah. So it's really okay.
It's less than one bit.
Less than one basis point of market penetration.
That's funny.
I was actually on a pitch call right before this explaining why I think stable coin
investments are interesting.
And I was like the TAM is all the money and all of the payments.
And we have not penetrated.
And even if you see these big chunky series A's for stable coin
companies, we're apparently at one bit of penetration.
Yes. My quick math is wrong.
It's six bits.
So yeah, but still, I mean, it's like minuscule, right?
I can't even do the math in my head.
It's just I had to use I had to pull up my calculator on my computer.
So does this like discredit our estimate in some sense that we're only getting to
around six billion, six, seven billion of monthly volume for stable coin payments?
I mean, I guess we're literally still early.
Yeah. I mean, I don't think so.
I mean, and I know you, you know, we talked about this before too.
I personally wanted a very conservative bottoms up like analysis.
I think just because of, I think there's too many like top line numbers floating around
that is not substantiated.
And there's like no nuance.
We know that state-of-the-art supplies are right at 240 something billion dollars
in supply.
But like that top line number is not, you know, it's like,
it's kind of meaningless by itself.
But by having bottoms up number, we know the minimum and it's growing a ton.
And I think that that is a far more useful metric than something like random top line number.
Yeah, I totally agree.
And I think, I actually think maybe we can start to move away
from those top down estimates a little bit,
because there's been so much consternation over them
between the Allium Visa estimate, the Coin Metrics estimate, the Artemis estimate.
Those are just heuristics and you're taking like literally hundreds of trillions
and you're trying to scrub out some types of transactions
and determine what's a valid payment.
What's in like some of its MEV, some of its exchange settlement.
I mean, it's interesting because a stablecoin transaction
for the purposes of trading or investment is not a non-economic,
that's still an economic transaction.
Yeah, but that's not a payment per se.
So that's just to be so clear with this study,
we're looking at payments in different modalities.
Yeah, no, that's that's a good point.
I think it's also in, you know, I think Citadel's like trading activity is not fake activity.
Citadel is a real company backed by very real investors.
And so I think that's a whole separate podcast about trading activity.
But yeah, you're totally right.
I know people are going to complain, so I want to anticipate this.
We're sharing aggregates.
Why are we doing that as opposed to going on a firm by firm basis?
Yeah, I mean, first of all, I think this is a very novel study
of highly sensitive data from each of these firms.
And you know, frankly, these firms, the stablecoin space is very hot right now.
There's a lot of competition and the firms just wouldn't
be comfortable sharing their individual numbers publicly.
And so the only way we can get any sense of like real bottoms up number is if I anonymize
and aggregate the numbers into like an aggregate figure.
But you know, we'll see.
I think my goal is honestly to just show the world that stablecoin payments are real.
And to the extent that these partners are comfortable sharing
whatever they want to share, I'm happy to accommodate.
Yeah.
And I think it's remarkable that we got the likes of Binance and
BVNK and REAP and Conduit to share data.
I mean, people don't realize how big Binance pay is on its own.
I mean, it's just an absolute behemoth.
So I credit honestly to your team
for persuading these PSPs to contribute their data.
Oh, thank you.
So another thing I want to add some color to is,
you know, we go through and on a country by country basis,
look at blockchain share and specific stablecoin share.
Generally speaking across the study, I think it's fair to say
Tether is about 90% of all the payments by volume.
Is that right?
Yeah.
But there is a lot of variance on a per country basis.
And partly that's because some countries just
didn't have as many data providers active.
And so, of course, you're going to see variance
due to smaller sample sizes.
Is that the right characterization?
Yep.
That's right.
I think there definitely is some regional differences.
And it's interesting to see, for example, that like
USDC has a lot more penetration in India, for example.
I actually don't even know.
I tried to do some background homework on why that's the case,
but I couldn't come to any specific reason.
I'm curious if you had a hypothesis.
No, that's a good question.
I don't know the answer.
There are some situations where the regional breakdown
in blockchains employed does have an explanation.
Like in Japan, XRP is actually used a fair amount.
That's because I think the Japanese have an affinity for Ripple.
Interesting.
As far as I know.
You don't know why that's the case.
I don't have a context on this.
I don't know either.
I don't know why.
I just know that it's a thing.
And then in terms of the blockchains,
we basically got similar results from our study last year,
which was not identical, though,
because Tron was the number one by volumes,
whereas in our study last year,
Ethereum was the number one by the survey.
I think it was Tron, Ethereum, Binance, Smart Chain, Polygon.
Is that right?
Am I getting that order right?
Yeah, I think those are the top.
I remember the top three was Ethereum, Binance, and Polygon, I think.
I was looking at this morning.
On the subsectors, we have B2B.
That's the biggest one.
P2P is the most mature.
It's actually flat.
That's the only sector that's not growing.
Then you have card link payments.
And then pre-funding.
Do you want to dig into a couple of those sectors
and explain what they mean?
Yeah, so for B2B, that's the most obvious one.
So that's basically business-to-business payments
that are likely, say, a retailer that is paying its supplier,
likely across the border.
Let's say you're like an Amazon store or like a retailer in Latin America,
and you're buying goods from China to resell.
That's an example of B2B.
And then card would be stablecoin-backed cards.
And so these are prepaid and debit cards
that you can swipe at any sort of Visa POS system
and basically pay the merchant in stablecoins.
And B2C actually technically should probably be C2B
because these are a lot of checkout volumes,
as well as B2C.
So these are like payout volumes.
So if you're a business that's paying out for payroll
or the other way around,
you're a consumer purchasing something from a business
and you're checking out with, say, like Binance Pay.
That's volume that's included in this B2C bucket.
Yeah, and then I guess P2P is what we're calling remittance
or just Venmo-style transfers type thing.
Yes.
I think the one call-out is that the P2P volumes
is just for the sampled firms
and does not include any sort of data
that's outside of the companies we surveyed.
If you just look at on-chain data,
the P2P volume estimates are much, much larger, right?
Because any wallet paying any wallet
is in some sense probably P2P.
Yeah, that's a very important point.
Our estimate is probably radically conservative
on the P2P front because, of course,
you can just pay someone with a stable coin.
You don't have to tell anyone about it.
Our methodology here is we're going
through the intermediaries.
So it'd only be if you made a P2P payment
through one of these firms,
through a Felix Pago, for instance,
that it would be counted in the survey.
So again, the data is very conservative,
but we wanted to characterize the transactions
where we know who's on the sending and receiving side,
where we know there's a real payment being made, basically.
Yep, do that.
So in addition to the partners, hopefully they come back.
I personally want to run this every quarter.
I'd love to bolster this and keep doing it,
keep growing it, add new data partners
because it's probably another couple dozen.
There's also a bunch of estimates.
So we had 11 other additional estimates
which we made including maybe controversially Bridge.
I mean, that's a very salient one.
I mean, how can you not include Bridge?
So tell us a little bit about how we made those estimates.
Yeah, I mean, for Bridge, I mean, luckily,
during the Stripe sessions
that was hosted a couple of weeks ago,
Stripe shared a Stripe versus Bridge growth chart, I think.
And so I think with that chart, plus some,
I think with that chart, plus some sort of VC estimates
on triangulating what folks have seen their volumes are
against the timeline,
we did a super rough estimate of likely volumes
given that we sort of know what the shape of the graph looks like
and backed into the Bridge volume data.
Yeah, and the remainder of it was mainly official dashboards
maintained by some of these projects
that their transactions hit the blockchain.
So we were able to get those numbers pretty easily.
So forgive me if I'm wrong,
this is basically the first study of its sort
that's ever been done.
Yeah, I think so.
I think actually from talking to some of the data partners,
many of them have tried to do something similar,
but I think it's hard if you're like, right,
it's like if you're not a neutral party,
it's hard to pass your competitors
to give you their volume data.
And so I think we saw this unique opportunity
as like this neutral data provider
to kind of like be the Switzerland of the space
and help kind of gather this sensitive data,
put it together, anonymize it so that it's confidential,
but we can still paint a really accurate
and positive story about stablecoins,
which again, there's a lot of fluff out there,
but like first time that we have some real data
that of transactions that are KYB getting KYC,
I think that's just like unheard of.
Yeah, and I mean, again, I'm kind of in awe of the fact
that the three of us, Castle Island, Dragonfly,
and Artemis are considered neutral,
but I'm glad people are trusting us with it.
So you guys are becoming a bit of a clearinghouse
for stablecoin data.
I mean, that is a core part of what Artemis does, right?
Yeah, we very much believe in an open finance network
and I was a early engineer at Venmo.
I firsthand know how awful it is
to work with legacy payment systems
that are very locale specific.
And so, I mean, stablecoins just to me is a no-brainer
for like this borderless finance.
That's the term, I think,
one of the Colson Brothers used during Stripe sessions.
And I think with this idea of borderless finance,
there also can be this like sort of borderless
mission control payments data kind of provider.
And so that's kind of where we want to be.
We want to be this like sort of
mission control for the entire space.
So we have this fancy new domain that we bought.
What is it?
Stablecoin.FYI, is that it?
Yes, that's right.
Stablecoin.FYI.
So that is where this data is going to live, by the way.
So you actually don't have to read a PDF anymore.
It's on there.
And you also have your market map,
the now famous Artemis market map alongside.
I mean, you guys also just have general
like stablecoin data on the website too.
Yeah, yeah, it's funny.
I lost a lot of hair trying to get one of these fancy URLs.
Had to go through some bidding wars and all that stuff.
And so I ended up buying it from a nice gentleman in London
who was squatting on this domain for a while.
And so I just like LinkedIn messaged him
and asked him if he would sell it to me.
And we had a bunch of negotiations
and got the deal done just in time.
Well done.
Yeah, I mean, good for him, I guess.
A little prescient.
And then the cover image.
What's on the cover of this study?
Tell us about that.
I think you should do the honors.
You're the, you're all about the tubes.
All right, so in case you're not familiar
and if you're born, you know, anytime after 1980
you've probably never seen one of these.
Have you ever used one of these pneumatic tubes?
No, but one story is that I,
so I also used to work at Google back in like 2010
and their New York office
is in a, the former like New York postal off,
like, yeah, like post services headquarters.
And so if you're in the Google office here in New York
they just have these like pneumatic tubes everywhere
or you can like shove in a letter
and it just like flies to another floor.
So does that still work?
I don't think so.
Well, so anyway, this used to be a thing in offices
before email or Slack, I guess, in hospitals and banks
and actually some like drive-throughs.
Like if you do drive-through banking,
which I've never done, you can sometimes use it.
It's a pneumatic.
So there's a canister goes in a pneumatic tube.
I don't know how the technology works
to route the tube to its destination.
But anyway, that's our analogy.
We're thinking of stable coins, the series of tubes
that span the globes.
The point is that people think stable coins
are like people creating a new form of money.
I think that's wrong.
I think it's just like cash.
Think of cash and you can send it anywhere
on the planet instantaneously.
That's how we should think about stable coins.
We're not really engaging in money creation.
For every unit of a stable coin
that you're creating every liability,
there's a corresponding asset,
which is like a treasury held in reserve.
So that's why we did the tube analogy to point out
we're just moving bundles of cash in a digital form
and the stable coins are a big tube network.
So that's the point.
Yeah, and I think I also like it
because I always see, just like maybe broadening this a bit,
I also see crypto as infrastructure for any asset.
And so it's kind of like the equivalent of these tubes
where you can tokenize anything.
It could be cash.
It could be equities at some point maybe.
I think Kraken is trying to do something like that.
I know that was something that you guys mentioned
in your podcast like a week ago.
And that in many cases doesn't make sense
to reinvent what cash is.
But crypto I think is very great
for this borderless finance.
Starlink, I mean, in your words,
Starlink for finance use case.
Yeah, I actually like that metaphor a lot better
than the room temperature superconductor for finance,
which is what the Stripe guys call stable coins.
Because Starlink actually works and exists
and room temp superconductors don't.
They're theoretical, so.
Yeah, that's true.
I got confused the first time around
because I had heard that because I'm like, wait,
but I thought they debunked this whole room temperature
superconductor thing.
So is this saying that crypto is fake?
Yeah, those ended up not being real.
Whereas Starlink for finance, the whole point is Starlink
brings billions of people online for the first time
that were not online.
Stable coins bring those online people into the economy
in a way they weren't able to participate before.
They didn't have access to dollar banking.
They couldn't receive payroll directly
from some offshore firm.
They had to do expensive remittances
or expensive cross-border payments on the B2B side.
So it puts the whole global population
on an equal stead for the first time.
People don't understand, I think, how exclusionary
and how expensive it gets if you're not near
to one of the main nodes on the dollar network.
So the further away you are from London
or from Hong Kong or from New York,
the more expensive it is to do business.
And you can't go directly from Mexico to the Philippines.
You have to go through the node.
So stable coins radically change that.
Now, in terms of your wishlist, like we've done two,
I think pretty groundbreaking studies
not to pat ourselves on the back too much,
but we've created information that we wanted
that didn't exist, right?
So we went and found it.
What is on your, what's next?
What's next for Artemis?
What do you want to know about stable coins?
You know, I think we talked about this a little earlier
where our estimate for coverage here
is maybe this 75% kind of like range.
And, you know, I would love to get more folks on board,
you know, notably missing, obviously,
it's like Coinbase from this study.
And so, you know, and a couple of the larger exchanges
in Asia too, I think like OKEx, Bybit and folks.
And so my dream is to have
as much like perfect coverage as possible.
And then furthermore, like if possible,
just like drill down into the use cases more kind of granularly.
Because again, it's like we hear this across the board
from whether it's, you know, Congressmen,
you know, when I was talking to like various folks in Congress,
like they are also asking like, hey, what are we,
what are stable coins being used for?
And like, we're not able to really answer
that question beyond this high level.
And I think that would go a long way, for example,
to just like keep pushing this genius bill through.
And so, again, just setting more data,
more granularity, more specificity.
And so if you're a stable coin player,
orchestrator, PSP, and you listen to the podcast,
you know, let us, let Nick or, you know,
if you want to be joining in our next, yeah, stable coin report.
Yeah, totally.
Well, thanks for, you know,
bringing this study to us and working with us.
I think we're very, very happy with the result.
And congrats for, you know, your success
in the stable coin realm is the kind of data provider of choice there.
So yeah, thanks for joining us today.
Thanks, Nick.
Yeah, thanks for having me and being down to collaborate on this report.
I think it's, yeah, it's been a joy working with you
and the team and Wyatt and Henry.
And yeah, we'll love to do this again.
Yeah, next quarter, we'll run it back.